Thank
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): you, Mr. Chairman. I appreciate the opportunity to be here and regret the fact that I missed your opening statements as I have another committee with hearings going on at the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): same time. It's one of the cruel tricks that the Senate plays on a person, multiple hearing obligations at the same time, but I'm very
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): glad to be with you here today. My staff all jokes, but they know that it's very serious that I do have favorites among committees, and my favorite
is judiciary.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Senator Paul also has a competing hearing in the Foreign Relations Committee. He wanted to be here today to introduce Justin
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Walker from his home state of Kentucky. I agreed to deliver that for him today. He says, "I regret that I'm not able to introduce Justin Walker in person, as I must
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): be in another committee hearing."
I am
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): confident that Justin will be a tireless defender of the Constitution and an impartial jurist who treats all who come before him with the respect they deserve.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): I fully support his confirmation.
I want to
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): echo the words of Senator Paul and what I imagine to have been the words of Senator McConnell who was here earlier. I've known Justin Walker for four or five years. I've found him to be an absolutely outstanding attorney, a true lawyer's lawyer.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Lawyers like Justin Walker can't be found many places. And whenever one can find a lawyer like Justin Walker who's willing to serve on the federal judiciary, I think we should all count ourselves lucky for that moment.
I can
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): tell you with a high degree of confidence, both
as a
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): member of the Senate Judiciary Committee for the last eight and a half years, and as a lawyer for the last two decades,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): that there are judges who come from different backgrounds. Some people come to the federal district court as a judge with a lot of trial experience or with a lot of fact gathering experience, experience doing a lot of depositions or a lot of witness cross-examinations in the courtroom. Others come with a lot of writing experience.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Now, while the former might seem more obvious as a qualifier, the latter is every bit as important, and in many ways, more rare. So when we have someone like Justin Walker, who's a law professor, who's written countless articles, who's written dispositive motions, appellate briefs, we have someone who will come to the federal district court well prepared to deal with what is in many ways the most difficult part of a job.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): which is addressing dispositive motions. Motions to dismiss, for example, under Rule 12b6. Motions for summary judgment under Rule 56. These are very difficult things to learn. They can't simply be taught. They're very difficult to acquire while on the job. I'm confident that Justin Walker is more than up to the task in that regard.
Mr.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Canterbury, I'd like to talk to you for a minute. In 2013, after the Sandy Hook shooting, you wrote a piece titled The Responsibility of Leadership in the Fraternal Order of Police Journal. In the piece, you stated that the FOP has a standing resolution, one that was passed at the 1993 National Conference to support the assault weapons
ban that
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): was passed by Congress in 1994.
Are
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): you now personally supportive of an assault weapons ban?
Sir, at our last
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): national conference, the delegates overturned that standing rule. And
as an
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): advocate for the FOP, it's been my position that I support what the members voted on by a motion. So as ATF director, looking through a different set of lens, I would much prefer to talk with the expert witnesses at ATF and the other professional staff but
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): I would render an opinion on the ban. So as a law enforcement professional, my job would be to enforce the laws that Congress implements.
Speaker 5: Understood. So if I understand you correctly, you're saying your position is consistent with and materially
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): indistinguishable from that of the FOP.
As FOP
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): president, Senator, it's my job to be the spokesperson for the resolutions and motions passed by my elected body. So
Speaker 7: prior to the time
that the F.O.
Speaker 7: FOP removed its support for that,
you
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): were supportive. The FOP was supportive, yes, sir,
Mr.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Senator. And you were personally being a member and president of FOP prior to that position change. Yes. Do you
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): support limitations on magazine
size?
Again,
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): Senator, the FOP's position is that we don't support any legislation as far as restriction on firearms at this point. As an ATF nominee, I believe it's my responsibility to enforce the laws that are passed by Congress, and I would make sure that every agent working for me would understand that.
Do
Speaker 8: you support universal background
checks?
The best
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): information that we can have in the NIC system is great, but as far as the legislation of universal background checks, I would have to look at the exact language to have a firm opinion on that, but I do believe that state and local agencies should be
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): encouraged to get quick, concise, and accurate information into the NICS system.
-
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): Do you still support waiting periods for handgun background checks, including in cases where the purchaser already owns a firearm?
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): - That was a national FOP position back in the early '90s. We support the system that's in place with the instant check with NICS as an organization. And as Senator Feinstein said, there's been a number of people
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): who attempted to purchase firearms
Speaker 9: that NICS prevented.
-
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): Mr. Chairman, I just noticed my time has expired. Can I ask one more question?
So, help me
Speaker 10: understand, are you telling me you have no positions independent of the FOP relative to firearms? And if so, how are we as a committee to evaluate where you stand on questions of policy? I understand and appreciate the fact
that
Speaker 10: you respect the fact that if you're confirmed to this position, you'll be expected to follow the law and that you'll
do so.
Speaker 10: I assume you can understand why we would still be interested in knowing where you come from on questions of policy, given the enormous discretion that someone in the position of ATF director has. Talking about promulgating regulations, making changes to them from time to time, regulations that have profound impacts that essentially change
the law.
Are you
Speaker 10: telling me that you have no positions that are analytically distinct from those of the FOP?
-
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): Senator, I would have my own personal opinions based on my experience, but I also believe as the head of a law enforcement agency, it's very difficult. I believe that I would work with the staff at ATF and the professionals at ATF and through the Department of Justice, the policy decisions,
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): require a process within the Department of Justice, and I would follow those rules for those policy decisions. And as the ATF Director, my positions that I held at the Fraternal Order of Police were the positions of the Fraternal Order of Police. That was my responsibility. But I'm a strong supporter of the Second Amendment. I believe in the right to bear arms.
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): And I would work with this committee on any proposed changes in litigation, but I would want to see those changes and have the expertise of the career staff at ATF to make those decisions.
-
Speaker 12: Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I've got additional questions, but we'll have to save those for a second round.